[
  {
    "id": "1",
    "lords_day" : "1",
    "question" : "What is your only comfort in life and in death?",
    "answer" : "That I am not my own,[1] but belong with body and soul, both in life and in death,[2] to my faithful Saviour Jesus Christ.[3] He has fully paid for all my sins with His precious blood, and has set me free from all the power of the devil.[5] He also preserves me in such a way[6] that without the will of my heavenly Father not a hair can fall from my head;[7] indeed, all things must work together for my salvation.[8] Therefore, by His Holy Spirit He also assures me of eternal life[9] and makes me heartily willing and ready from now on to live for Him.[10]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "1 Cor 6:19, 20",
      "Rom 14:7-9",
      "1 Cor 3:23; Tit 2:14",
      "1 Pet 1:18, 19; 1 John 1:7; 2:2",
      "John 8:34-36; Heb 2:14, 15; 1 John 3:8",
      "John 6:39, 40; 10:27-30; 2 Thess 3:3; 1 Pet 1:5",
      "Matt 10:29-31; Luke 21:16-18",
      "Rom 8:28",
      "Rom 8:15, 16; 2 Cor 1:21, 22; 5:5; Eph 1:13, 14",
      "Rom 8:14"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "2",
    "lords_day" : "1",
    "question" : "What do you need to know in order to live and die in the joy of this comfort?",
    "answer" : "First, how great my sins and misery are;[1] second, how I am delivered from all my sins and misery;[2] third, how I am to be thankful to God for such deliverance.[3]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Rom 3:9, 10; 1 John 1:10",
      "John 17:3; Acts 4:12; 10:43",
      "Matt 5:16; Rom 6:13; Eph 5:8-10; 1 Pet 2:9, 10"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "3",
    "lords_day" : "2",
    "question" : "From where do you know your misery?",
    "answer" : "From the Law of God.1",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Rom 3:20; Rom 7:7"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "4",
    "lords_day" : "2",
    "question" : "What does the Law of God require of us?",
    "answer" : "Christ teaches us in sum, Matthew 22, “You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your mind. This is the first and great commandment. And the second is like it: You shall love your neighbor as yourself. On these two commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.”1",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Matt 22:37–40; Lk 10:27; Deut 6:5; Gal 5:14"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "5",
    "lords_day" : "2",
    "question" : "Can you keep all this perfectly?",
    "answer" : "No,1 for I am prone by nature to hate God and my neighbor.2",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Rom 3:10–12, 23; 1 John 1:8, 10",
      "Rom 8:7; Eph 2:3"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "6",
    "lords_day" : "3",
    "question" : "Did God create man thus, wicked and perverse?",
    "answer" : "No,1 but God created man good and after His own image,2 that is, in righteousness and true holiness, that he might rightly know God his Creator, heartily love Him, and live with Him in eternal blessedness, to praise and glorify Him.3",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Gen 1:31",
      "Gen 1:26–27",
      "2 Cor 3:18; Col 3:10; Eph 4:24"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "7",
    "lords_day" : "3",
    "question" : "From where, then, did man's depraved nature come?",
    "answer" : "From the fall and disobedience of our first parents, Adam and Eve, in Paradise,[1] for there our nature became so corrupt[2] that we are all conceived and born in sin.[3]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Gen 3",
      "Rom 5:12, 18–19",
      "Ps 51:5;"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "8",
    "lords_day" : "3",
    "question" : "But are we so corrupt that we are totally unable to do any good and inclined to all evil?",
    "answer" : "Yes,[1] unless we are regenerated by the Spirit of God.[2]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Gen 6:5; 8:21; Job 14:4; Is 53:6",
      "John 3:3-5"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "9",
    "lords_day" : "4",
    "question" : "Is God, then, not unjust by requiring in His law what man cannot do?",
    "answer" : "No, for God so created man that he was able to do it.[1] But man, at the instigation of the devil,[2] in deliberate disobedience[3] robbed himself and all his descendants of these gifts.[4]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Gen 1:31",
      "Gen 3:13; John 8:44; 1 Tim 2:13, 14",
      "Gen 3:6",
      "Rom 5:12, 18, 19"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "10",
    "lords_day" : "4",
    "question" : "Will God allow such disobedience and apostasy to go unpunished?",
    "answer" : "Certainly not. He is terribly displeased with our original sin as well as our actual sins. Therefore He will punish them by a just judgment both now and eternally,[1] as He has declared:[2] Cursed be every one who does not abide by all things written in the book of the law, and do them (Galatians 3:10).",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Ex 34:7; Ps 5:4-6; 7:10; Nah 1:2; Rom 1:18; 5:12; Eph 5:6; Heb 9:27",
      "Deut 27:26"
    ]
  },
  {
    "id": "11",
    "lords_day" : "4",
    "question" : "But is God not also merciful?",
    "answer" : "God is indeed merciful,[1] but He is also just.[2] His justice requires that sin committed against the most high majesty of God also be punished with the most severe, that is, with everlasting, punishment of body and soul.[3]",
    "footnotes" : [
      "Ex 20:6; 34:6, 7; Ps 103:8, 9",
      "Ex 20:5; 34:7; Deut 7:9-11; Ps 5:4-6; Heb 10:30, 31",
      "Matt 25:45,46"
    ]
  }
]